Guide to the Cap and Gown Club Records, 1908-1978 CTC.1980.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Cap and Gown Club Records
1908-1978
CTC.1980.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
The University of Pittsburgh's Cap and Gown Club was an all male organization that annually wrote and produced a varsity musical comedy show. The Club produced 36 shows between 1908 and 1947, the annual sequence interrupted only by World War II. Their records consist primarily of programs, which are supplemented with clippings, photographs, miscellaneous correspondence, and club minutes. Digital reproductions of the Cap and Gown programs and photographs are available online.
Cap and Gown Club (Pittsburgh, Pa.).
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically. Links to digitized images of the individual programs are available in the Collection Inventory; selected photographs were scanned and added to the University of Pittsburgh Historic Photographs collection.
History
Pitt’s Cap and Gown Club was an all male organization devoted to the production of annual varsity musical comedy shows. Founded in 1908, it eventually became the most popular non-athletic activity on campus. The Club produced a total of 36 shows through 1947, halting their activities only for four years during World War II. The Graduate Cap and Gown club, which supervised the productions, was officially incorporated in 1928 although it had been in existence for some years before. This group was officially dissolved in 1978. All Cap and Gown productions were written and produced by Pitt undergraduates and alumni. Only undergraduates made up the casts and chorus. Gene Kelly, CAS ’33, was an undergraduate member, and served as the Club’s dance director for several years after graduating. Regis Toomey, ’21, was another member who went on to a successful theatrical career. The Cap and Gown Club also produced two songs that became University standards, “Hail to Pitt” (from 1910's Here and There) and the “Pitt Victory Song” (from 1938's Pickets Please).
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Cap and Gown Club consist primarily of production programs, arranged chronologically, with related material such as clippings, photographs, etc., of which there is little, filed with the appropriate program. A few of the programs contain music. Programs from the 1911 and 1919 shows are missing. Additional material includes photocopies of various articles on the Cap and Gown Club from The Pitt Panther, miscellaneous correspondence and memorabilia, and the final club minutes of 1978.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Materials collected by Special Collections staff during the 1960s and 1970s. Additional items donated by Ardis Jones Blenko in May 1980 and Stephen Witmer in December 2010. The music score for 1937’s Trailer Ho by John Stephens donated by his widow Lenore Stephens in May 2009.
Custodial History
Some of the materials were transferred from the University Archives in September 1981 to supplement those already held in the Curtis Theatre Collection.
Previous Citation
Cap and Gown Club Records, 1908-1978, CTC.1980.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Cap and Gown Club Records, 1908-1978, CTC.06, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
G. Norman Reis Papers, 1909-1946, CTC.1985.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Oliver P. Merriman Scrapbook Collection, 1825-1942, CTC.1964.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
University Archives, 0/3/1 Box 14 Starrett Historical files FF 79
Cap and Gown Club (Pittsburgh, Pa.).; Kelly, Gene, 1912-1996; Toomey, Regis, 1902-; University of Pittsburgh.; Actors and actresses -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Student activities -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater; Theater programs
- In Wupland, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- When Pitt Was Young, May 14, 1909 (Folder 2)
- Here and There, May 12, 1910 (Folder 3)
- Cupid's Capers, May 15, 1912 (Folder 4)
- Prince of Sham, April 1913 (Folder 5)
- The Little Suffragette, March 1914 (Folder 6)
- The Maxixe Girl, February 1915 (Folder 7)
- Suite Sixteen, February 1916 (Folder 8)
- Dr. Divorce, January 16, 1917 (Folder 9)
- Vaudeville show, March 1918 (Folder 10)
- The Diamond Girl, May 1920 (Folder 11)
- Done and Undone, April 1921 (Folder 12)
- Bound in Morocco, April 1922 (Folder 13)
- Leave it to Marian, May 1923 (Folder 14)
- All in a Day, May 1924 (Folder 15)
- Castles in Spain, May 1925 (Folder 16)
- The Red Moon, May 1926 (Folder 17)
- Miss Mannequin, 1927 (Folder 18)
- Mary-Grow-Round, May 1928 (Folder 19)
- Yip-Yip, May 1929 (Folder 20)
- Manhattan Preferred, April 1930 (Folder 21)
- What's Up, April 1931 (Folder 22)
- The Silver Domino, 1932 (Folder 23)
- All to the Point, 1933 (Folder 24)
- Hello Again, 1934 (Folder 25)
- In the Soup, May 1935 (Folder 26)
- Out for the Count, 1936 (Folder 27)
- Trailer Ho, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Trailer Ho - music scores, 1937 (Folder 2)
- Pickets Please, 1938 (Folder 3)
- At Your Service, 1939 (Folder 4)
- Snap Your Fingers, April 1940 (Folder 5)
- Snap Your Fingers - music scores, 1940 (Folder 6)
- Head Over Heels, April 1941 (Folder 7)
- Kilroy is Here, December 1946 (Folder 8)
- Mabel's Fable, 1947 (Folder 9)
- Cap and Gown Club History (Folder 10)
- Meeting minutes, 1963, 1978 (Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1908-1947 (Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous (Folder 13)